本劇改編自聖經  它們曾改變世界
本劇將始終保持《聖經》真諦
《聖經》前情提要
Previously on The Bible.
耶路撒冷，我們的新家園
Jerusalem, our new home.
猶太人民，打造了一個王國
The Jewish people have forged a kingdom...
在應許之地
in the promised land.
但是他們一直不斷的為的生存戰鬥
But their survival has been a constant struggle.
他們被很多大國包圍著
Surrounded by great superpowers...
他們一直受到壓迫
They have been oppressed...
奴役
Enslaved...
和流亡
and exiled.
每一次，都會有一個偉大的猶太英雄來幫助他們
Each time, a great Jewish hero has come to their aid.
主啊
Lord!
但現在
But now...
他們已經屈服於羅馬的威力
they've succumbed to the might of Rome.
前進
Forward!
以色列遭受前所未有的災難
Israel suffers like never before.
人們渴望一個救世主
The people crave a saviour,
一個彌撒亞（救世主）
a messiah.
《聖經》
第06集-盼望
在叛亂中的耶路撒冷
Rebellion in Jerusalem.
這邊
This way.
一只代表羅馬帝國的老鷹懸於新的猶大聖殿之上
A Roman eagle soars above the Jews' holy temple...
這對是其信仰的侮辱
an abomination to their faith.
快點
Be quick!
必須把它拆下來
It must be removed.
-有士兵  -逮捕他們
- Guards! - Arrest them!
抓住他們
Hold them off!
快點
Hurry!
快差不多了
Almost there!
帶他們走
Bring them!
老鷹是由猶大人的王
The eagle was put on the temple by the king of the Jews,
希律大帝放上去的
Herod the Great...
一位由羅馬人推上寶座的貴族
A nobleman placed on the throne by the Romans.
再忍一下就好
Just one more.
好了
There.
夠了  夠了
Enough! Enough!
把你們的臟手拿開
Take your butchering hands off me,
不然我就砍了它們
or I will have them removed.
想拆除老鷹的人
Ah, the bird men.
過來  認為我對你們的聖殿來說
Come. My little rebels...
不夠幹凈  不夠聖潔  猶太血統
who think I am not clean enough or pure enough...
不夠純正的叛徒
or Jewish enough for your holy temple!
那麼我告訴你們
Well, let me tell you something.
聖殿是我建的
I built the holy temple!
是我建的
I built it!
我要是選擇放一只鳥在上面
And if I choose to put a bird on the top...
讓我的羅馬朋友高興的話
to keep my Roman friends happy,
心存感激吧
be grateful.
因為如果你們覺得我難以忍受
Because if you think that I'm hard to live with,
那你們去跟他們接觸接觸試試
you should try living with them.
啊
Ah.
猶太人渴望在自己的領土上獲得自由
The Jews long for freedom in their own land.
從首都耶路撒冷
From the capital, Jerusalem,
到貧苦偏僻的加利利
to the provincial backwater of Galilee,
人們靠他們的信仰
the people take comfort in their faith...
彼此聊以慰藉
and each other.
馬利亞  我的未婚妻
Mary, my betrothed,
你有著我所見過最迷人的雙眼
you have the most beautiful eyes I've ever seen...
和最甜美的笑容
and the sweetest smile.
奉希律王和羅馬之名
In the name of Herod and Rome...
快繳稅
Taxes are owed!
-這是在幹嘛  -把這個男人帶走
- What is this? - We will take this man.
沒看出來你們打擾誦經了嗎
Can't you see you're interrupting the Scriptures?
-還有你  -不
- And you. - No!
這肯定是個誤會  我們在這兒敬拜上帝
This must be a mistake. We're worshipping God here.
你們的上帝不關我們的事
Your God, your problem.
約瑟   走吧
- Joseph! - Come on!
這是上帝的聖地
This is the house of God!
抓住它!
Take it!
該付錢啦
Time to pay up!
快去你父親家   快
Get back to your father's house.Be quick.
付錢 ！什麼都不留下！
Pay up! Leave nothing!
帶那些女人回來
Bring those women back!
快走
Move!
讓開
Get out of my way!
馬利亞
Mary.
還給我
Give that back!
馬利亞
Mary.
上帝與你同在
The Lord is with you.
不要害怕
Don't be afraid.
很快你將誕下一子
You will soon give birth to a son.
他將會是至高神的兒子
He will be the Son of the Most High.
聖靈將會降臨你腹中
The Holy Spirit will move in you.
不要害怕
Don't be afraid.
我是上帝的僕人
I am the Lord's servant.
所要生的聖者
The Holy One to be born...
必稱為神的兒子
will be called the Son of God.
馬利亞
Mary!
告訴我發生了什麼  馬利亞  求你  不能在這說  不能在這說
Tell me what's going on, Mary, please! Not here, not here.
你懷孕了
You're pregnant.
你做了什麼  -你到底都做了什麼
What have you done? What on earth have you done?
沒有別人  我發誓
There has been no one, I swear.
肯定有別人  我又不傻
Well, there's been someone. I'm not stupid.
我仍是處女之身
I'm still a virgin.
這是神的作為
This is the work of God.
我不知道為什麼會選中我   但我說的都是實話
I don't know why I've been chosen, but I'm telling you the truth.
請你相信我
You must believe me.
我曾以為我了解你
I thought I knew you.
求你了  約瑟
Please. Please, Joseph.
我要你做我丈夫
I need you to be my husband.
我要你做孩子的父親
I need you to be the father of this child.
他是上帝之子
The Child of God.
求你  我的愛人  求你相信我
Please, my love. Please trust me.
馬利亞  上帝是不會選中我們這種人的
Mary, God doesn't do this to people like us.
上帝啊  如果這是您的作為  請幫幫我吧
If this be your work, Lord, please help...
幫幫我們
help us.
大衛的子孫約瑟
Joseph, son of David.
不要怕
Be at peace.
只管娶過你的妻子馬利亞來
Take Mary as your wife.
她是純潔的
She is pure.
因她所懷的孕  是從聖靈來的
The child she carries is from God.
-盪婦
Jezebel!
-無恥  無恥的淫婦
Shameless. Shameless whore!
不是我的錯  是上帝選中了我
It's not my fault God chose me.
不是我自願的
I didn't ask for this to happen!
她懂什麼
What does she know about anything?
她倒是懂得怎麼勾引男人
She knows enough to get pregnant.
-事到如今誰還會娶你  -我會
- Who'll have you now? - I will!
我相信她
I believe her!
我會娶她為妻
And I will take her as my wife!
只要她還願意嫁我
If she'll still have me.
結婚數月後
Within a few months of marrying,
約瑟和馬利亞就被迫離開了拿撒勒
Joseph and Mary are forced to leave Nazareth.
馬利亞
Mary?
準備好了嗎
You ready?
為了更好地控制他們的臣民
To better control their subjects,
羅馬開始了大普查
Rome has ordered a census.
所有人都必須返回其出生地
All men must return to the town of their birth.
好了
Right.
走
Come on.
約瑟帶著新婚妻子趕往伯利恆
Joseph takes his new wife to Bethlehem.
路途遙遠  道阻且長
A hundred miles of treacherous open road,
臨盆在即
with a baby due any day.
馬利亞和約瑟以兩人之力與世為敵
Mary and Joseph are alone against the world,
但人們正在朝他們聚攏而來
but others are being drawn towards them.
摩西時代曾有一條預言
A prophecy from the time of Moses...
斷言了猶太民族一個偉大的王的降生
predicts the birth of a great king of the Jews...
上天會示下
announced in the heavens.
有星要出於雅各
A star shall come out of Jacob...
有杖要興於以色列
and a sceptre shall rise out of Israel.
堅持住
Hold on!
要生了  約瑟  要生了
He's coming now. He's coming. Joseph! He's coming!
堅持住  我去找個庇護所
Hold on! I'm gonna find somewhere.
有人嗎
Hello?
-回來  他要降生了  -能幫幫我們嗎
- He's coming! - Can anybody help us?
他要降生了  約瑟  現在
He's coming, Joseph, now!
我來了  好吧  來吧
I'm coming! All right. Come on.
堅持住
Hold on!
跟緊我
Stay with me.
陛下  占星師巴爾薩扎覲見
Sire. The astrologer Balthazar.
巴爾薩扎
Balthazar.
過來
Come.
喝點酒嗎
Wine?
謝謝您的款待  陛下
You're very gracious, Your Majesty.
我就不用了
I'd rather not.
我很好奇  對那將來的新王您知道些什麼
I wonder, what can you tell me of the new king?
-王  -猶太人的王
King? Of the Jews.
有他的消息嗎
Yes. What news of him?
猶太人的王
King of the Jews?
我是不是聽錯了
Am I missing something?
你來這兒不就是
Did you not come here...
覲見猶太人的王嗎
to see the king of the Jews?
你現在看到的希律王
Are you not looking at Herod,
難道不是猶太人的王嗎
king of the Jews?
當然是
Of course.
那還有誰自稱為王
Then who is claiming to be king?
現在還沒有  他尚未出世
No one. He's not born yet.
這是一個預言  星宿昭示了他的降臨
It is a prophecy heralded by the star.
您的文士肯定也收到了啟示
Surely your scribes have received the revelation.
星宿  預言
Stars! Prophecies!
你打斷我進餐就為了這個
You interrupt my meal for this?
如果你不介意的話  回去吧
Please, if you don't mind.
希律王什麼也不知道
Herod knows nothing.
跟著星星走
We follow the star.
那個大逆不道的預言會在哪裡應驗
Where is this treacherous prophecy?
找到了嗎
Have you found it?
-在這兒
Ah, here.
讀給我聽  "以賽亞...
Read it! 「Isaiah.
因此主自己要給你們一個兆頭"
Therefore, the Lord himself will give a sign.」
看  看那兒
Look. Look. There.
"必有童女懷孕生子"
「A young woman will conceive and give birth to a son.」
請幫幫我們
Help us! Please!
"他名稱為奇妙..."
「He will be called Wonderful.」
馬利亞  我扶著你
Mary! I've got you.
"策士..."
「Counsellor.」
請幫幫我們
Help us, please!
跟我來  "全能的神..."
Follow me. "Mighty God."
Sir, we need help!
"永在的父..."  快
"Everlasting Father." Quickly!
"和平的君"  這裡會是乾的
- Prince of Peace. - It'll be dry in here.
加油  加油
Come on. Come on.
但我才是帶來和平的人
But I am the one who brings peace!
你覺得一個孩子能做到嗎
Do you think some child could do that?
預言裡說沒說這個"和平的君"將在哪裡降生
Is it written where this mighty prince will be born?
米迦說他將出生在伯利恆
Micah says it will be Bethlehem.
伯利恆...
Bethlehem.
在伯利恆
Bethlehem!
集合部隊
Gather the troops!
我們的兒子..
Our son.
感謝上帝
Thanks be to God.
夫人  我相信您的兒子
Lady, I believe your son...
必是其子民未來的王
is the promised king of his people.
他叫什麼名字
What is his name?
耶穌
Jesus.
他的名字是耶穌
His name is Jesus.
馬利亞
Mary!
我們得走了  馬上出發
We have to leave. Now.
我也沒法解釋  相信我就好
I can't explain. Just trust me.
當希律王聽說有一位新的王在伯利恆誕生
When Herod hears a new king is being born in Bethlehem,
他便下令殺死所有嬰兒
he orders the murder of e very infant boy.
把你們找到的嬰兒都殺死
Kill any you find!
這邊
This way.
不
No.
快  都抓起來
Quickly! Get 'em all!
我的兒子
My son!
搶下那個男孩
Take the boy.
不
No!
這是對無辜平民的屠殺
The massacre of the innocents.
只有一個孩子免於此難
One child escapes.
希律王永遠不會知道
Herod will never know...
在伯利恆的屠殺   其實是徒勞無功
that the slaughter in Bethlehem was for nothing.
他也行將就木
He's dying...
他的最後一個偏執舉動
His last paranoid act...
就是以謀反的罪名處死了自己的長子
the execution of his eldest son for plotting against him.
父親  求你了
Father, please.
希律王死後
When Herod dies,
人民看到了重獲自由的希望
the people sense an opportunity to win their freedom.
以色列人爆發了
Israel explodes.
但羅馬人也沒有手軟
But the Roman response is brutal.
團結在一起
Keep together!
叛亂被殘酷地鎮壓了
The uprising is crushed.
僅加利利地區
In Galilee alone,
就有兩千人被釘十字架
2,000 are crucified.
耶穌和他的家人從埃及返回
Jesus and his family return from Egypt.
我們就快到了  耶穌
We're nearly there, Jesus.
馬上就到家了
We're almost home.
一個十年的黑暗已經籠罩著以色列
A decade of darkness has fallen over Israel.
約瑟
Joseph!
他們有何過錯
What have they done?
我們要相信上帝自有安排
We must trust in God's plan...
一如他信任我們
as he trusts in us.
羅馬帝國直接控制了將耶路撒冷和猶太地區
Rome has taken direct control of Jerusalem and Judaea.
希律的兒子安提帕正在等待著
Herod's son Antipas...
二十年來羅馬的第四任巡撫來臨
awaits the arrival of the fourth Roman governor in 20 years...
傲慢殘忍的本丟．彼拉多巡撫
the arrogant and ruthless Pontius Pilate.
歡迎  巡撫
Greetings, prefect.
歡迎來到猶太
Welcome to Judaea.
希望您能在這裡擁有一份充實
I hope your time here will be prosperous...
平和的生活
and peaceful.
我也正打算如此
I intend to make sure it is.
凱撒的命令
Orders from Caesar.
異教活動必須停止
This dissent must stop.
對於彼拉多和安提帕來說
For Pilate and Antipas,
任何群眾集會都具有威脅性
any gathering of people is a threat.
悔改吧  如此才能得到救贖
Repent! And your sins shall be forgiven.
在約旦河岸
At the River Jordan,
人們絡繹不絕地來找施洗約翰
crowds flocking to John the Baptist.
我為你們施洗  準備迎接新的國度吧
I baptise you, ready for the new kingdom.
你已潔凈
As you are cleansed,
所有以色列人也將和你一樣潔凈
so all Israel shall be cleansed!
你就是彌賽亞嗎
(指受膏者  即預言中的耶穌猶太人所期待的救世主)
Are you the messiah?
在這裡  我在等  在那等
- Here. I'm waiting. - Keep back here.
-你說有麻煩
You said there was trouble.
-在沙漠地帶   人們都成群結隊去找那個野人似的約翰
In the desert, the people are flocking to this wild man- John.
他們認為他是先知
They think he's a prophet.
甚至有人認為他就是彌賽亞
Some even call him the messiah.
你當真悔改了嗎
Do you truly repent?
上帝的斧頭已備好
God's axe is ready.
每個不結好果子的樹
Every tree that does not produce good fruit...
都將被砍下來  丟進火裡
will be cut down and thrown into the fire.
所有人都將見證神的救贖
All flesh shall see the salvation of God!
彌賽亞又是什麼
And what is a messiah?
是猶太人的救世主
The redeemer of the Jews.
受膏於上帝  來解放他們
Anointed by God to set them free.
那你可得好好留心這位彌賽亞了
Then you need to keep an eye on your messiah.
即將到來的那一位  大過我
There is one to come, greater than me,
他將用火來施洗
who will baptise with fire.
我不過是曠野中的吶喊
I am just a voice in the wilderness,
做好準備  迎接...
preparing the way for the...
主
Lord.
別停
Don't stop.
我理該當受你的洗啊
Surely I need you to baptise me.
約翰  你所行的是正道
John, what you are doing is right.
為我施洗吧
Baptise me.
受洗後  耶穌被聖靈帶進入曠野
After his baptism, Jesus enters the wilderness.
在曠野中的四十天  他的靈魂飽受考驗
For 40 days, his spirit is tested,
為他之後將要面臨的挑戰做準備
preparing him for the challenges to come.
撒但
Satan.
你若是  神的兒子
If you are the Son of God,
可以吩咐這石頭變成食物
command that this stone becomes bread.
但人活著
Man...
不是單靠食物
shall not live by bread alone,
乃是靠神口裡所出的一切話
but on every word that comes from the mouth of God.
如果上帝愛你
If God loves you,
可以從這裡跳下去
throw yourself down.
因為他的使者會用手托著你
His angels will lift you up in their hands.
你怎敢試探神
How dare you put God to the test!
你若在我面前下拜
If you will bow down and worship me,
我就把全世界都給你
I will give you the whole world.
釘死他
Crucify him!
撒但  走開
Get away from me, Satan.
我拜主我的神  我的上帝
I worship the Lord my God...
單要事奉他
and serve him only.
耶穌抵擋住了撒但的誘惑
Jesus resists Satan's temptations...
並準備開始完成他的使命
and prepares to begin his mission.
但施洗的約翰無法與他同行
But it will be without John the Baptist.
他已經被安提帕逮捕了
He has been arrested by Antipas.
快點  你這賤民
Come on, scum!
進去
Get in. In!
耶穌回到了他的家鄉加利利
遠離耶路撒冷政權
啟程前往內海海岸
他的使命始於這裡
需要幫忙嗎
Do you need help?
我不是在尋求幫助
I'm not looking for any help.
更何況  也沒什麼可幫的
And besides, there's nothing to help with.
你在幹什麼
Hey. What are you doing?
你不能就這麼爬上我的船
You can't just climb into my boat!
沒錯  你說得對  助我一臂之力吧
Yeah, you're right. Give me a helping hand.
你這是幹什麼呢
What do you think you're doing?
我們要去捕魚
We're going fishing.
大白天的  沒有魚可捕
There are no fish out there this time of day.
其實  什麼時候都捕不到魚
In fact, there are no fish out here any time of day.
彼得
Peter.
給我一小時
Just give me an hour,
我將給你一個全新的生活
and I will give you a whole new life.
誰說我想要什麼新生活了
Who says I want one?
都跟你說了
I tell you.
現在沒有魚可捕
There's no fish out there.
我該怎麼處置你呢
What am I going to do with you?
你  還有你那張危險的嘴
You and your dangerous mouth.
靜靜聆聽
Listen.
聽一個煽動暴亂的傻瓜嗎
To a seditious fool?
算了吧
I don't think so.
聽上帝的旨意
To God's message.
'天國近了'
The kingdom of heaven is near.
這麼說  你承認自己是彌賽亞了
So you do claim to be the messiah?
不
No.
但你認為他要來了
But you think he's coming.
不
No.
他已經來了
He's already here.
就在這裡
He's here.
在外面
Out there.
傳播神的真理
Speaking God's truth,
開啟人的心智
opening the hearts of all men.
這是怎麼回事
How did this happen?
你做了什麼
What did you do?
我在給你改變人生的機會
I'm giving you the chance to change your life.
彼得  來跟從我
Peter, come with me.
別再捕魚了  我要叫你
Give up catching fish, and I will make you...
得人如得魚一樣
a fisher of men.
我們要做什麼
What are we going to do?
改變世界
Change the world.
他將帶來正義與公平的新時代
He will bring a new age of righteousness and justice!
他的力量將帶領人類邁向新世界
His power will draw all men to a new world.
全人類
All People!
下集《聖經》預告
Next time on The Bible.
馬利亞  他回來了
Mary, he's here!
-誰  -耶穌  他終於回來了
Who? Jesus! He's back!
我聽說了一個年輕先知
I've had reports of a young prophet,
拿撒勒人耶穌
a Jesus of Nazareth.
他在加利利有一大批追隨者
He has a big following in Galilee.
傳聞說他會來耶路撒冷
It's rumoured he'll come to Jerusalem.
他能創造奇跡
He works miracles.
大家都這麼說
They all do.
虛心的人有福了  因為天國是他們的
Blessed are the poor, for theirs is the kingdom of heaven.
溫柔的人有福了  因為他們必承受地土
Blessed are the meek, for they shall inherit the earth.
你說什麼  你說你就是被上帝選中派來人間的彌賽亞嗎
What are you saying?  that you are the messiah,the chosen one sent by God?
不可能
No!
預言開始應驗了
It has begun.
有五千人前往見他
5,000 came to see him.
五千人
5,000.
有人說那個耶穌把一個死人救活了
They say this Jesus has raised a man from the dead.
凡活著信我的人必永遠不死
Whoever believes in me shall never die.
你會為此付出代價   正如你的朋友施洗約翰一樣
You will pay the price for this, like your friend John the Baptist!
過些日子我們就去耶路撒冷
Soon we go to Jerusalem.
那太危險了！
It's too dangerous.
耶穌從加利利來耶路撒冷過逾越節
The messiah from Galilee in Jerusalem at Passover. How timely.
如果他與萬千擁護者相伴而來
What if he comes with thousands of supporters?
隨著慶祝節日的人們相繼到來
The city will already be breaking at the seams...
這城將會人滿為患
with those arriving for the festival.
猶太人的王
King of the Jews!
你可以如軍隊般帶領我們
You can lead us like an army.
我們有能力擊敗羅馬人  不  不應該通過這種方式
- We're strong enough to beat the Romans! - No, this is not the way.
羅馬渣滓  羅馬強盜
Roman scum! Roman thieves!
要他們好看   羅馬強盜
Let us show them! Roman thieves!
彌賽亞  彌賽亞
Messiah! Messiah!
他們希望你做他們的王
They want you to be their king.
我們必須阻止這個神棍  這個騙子
We must not allow this miracle man, this fraud,
來破壞逾越節
to disrupt Passover.
倘若你們渴望看見公義
If you hunger for righteousness,
你們將透過我看見
you will be filled... through me.
這事彼拉多知道嗎
Does Pilate know?
嗯
Hmm.